Guide to the Edward K. Welsh Papers TAM.074
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Edward K. Welsh Papers
circa 1930-1974
1960-1969
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Welsh, Edward K., 1902-1979
Welsh, Miriam
TAM.074
4.25 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons and 5 folders
Edward K. Welsh (1902-1979) began his career as a union organizer in 1930. In the 1940s, he was hired by the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) to organize workers in the steel, auto, and textile industries in the United States. He later organized laborers at the Panama Canal Zone. In 1961, the AFL-CIO sent Welsh to Africa as part of the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (ICFTU) to assist various African trade union movements. He spent three and a half years in Africa. The collection mainly documents Welsh's trade union work in the United States and Africa, but also reflects some of his nonunion activities.
Related Archival Materials at the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
There are a small number of images of Edward K. Welsh in the Sam Reiss Photographs Collection - Part II- Photographic Prints (PHOTOS 021.001) and the Daniel Nilva Photographic Negatives Collection (PHOTOS 067).
Many collections at the Tamiment Library feature the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions. In particular, researchers may wish to consult the Printed Ephemera Collection on Trade Unions (PE 001).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Mirian Welsh, wife of Edward K. Welsh, in 1979, 1985, and 2007. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1979.004 and 1979.011.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Edward K. Welsh (1902-1979) was born in New York City in 1902. As a teenager, he worked at the old Metropolitan Opera House, opening carriage doors for opera-goers. He also worked as a laborer, ditch digger, elevator operator, store clerk, shipping clerk, and longshoreman.
Welsh's career in the labor movement began in 1930, when he worked as a volunteer organizer for the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), Local 22 (dressmakers). Soon he became involved in radical politics, traveling with Communist Party notable Jay Lovestone and others to the Soviet Union. During that visit, Stalin hoped to secure Welsh as one of communism's supporters among African Americans in the United States. However, Welsh's close-up exposure to Soviet society caused him to alter his political allegiance. Nevertheless, his concern for workers' rights led him to continue to carry out his activism in the labor movement through writing, speaking and teaching.
During the 1940s, Welsh was appointed to the staff of Allan Haywood, vice president and director of organization of the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), where he organized workers in the steel, auto, and textile industries in the South and in Ohio.
In 1950, Welsh was sent to the Panama Canal Zone by CIO president Philip Murray to organize workers there. With Welsh's help, 5,500 workers were enrolled in Local 900 of the Government and Civic Employees Organizing Committee within a year. In 1953, Welsh returned to New York City, where he organized office workers. He later moved to Detroit, where he conducted worker education and political action programs.
The CIO merged with the American Federation of Labor (AFL) in 1955. In 1961, AFL-CIO president George Meany assigned Welsh to the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (ICFTU). Welsh's job was to assist trade union movements in Africa, specifically in Tanganyika (now Tanzania), Kenya, and Uganda. During this period, the AFL-CIO sought out African union leaders to further the United States' political and economic interests in Africa. Sanctioned by the Department of State and the CIA, African labor leaders were given secret undercover support.
Welsh spent three and a half years in Africa organizing agricultural, textile, hotel, and building and construction workers. He returned to the United States in 1964 to work with taxicab drivers and hospital workers in New York City before retiring three years later. Welsh died in February 1979 at the age of 77.
Scope and Content Note
Roughly half of the collection chronicles Welsh's trade union work in both the United States and Africa for the CIO, AFL-CIO, and the ICFTU. Genres of materials which document these activities include correspondence, reports, photographs, minutes, speeches, and other materials. Earlier files from the 1930s through 1950s shed light on Welsh's organizing efforts in the United States for the CIO and the AFL-CIO, as well as some of his nonunion activities and his work in Panama. Later files from the late 1950s and 1960s focus on the ICFTU and Welsh's involvement with the organization. The other half of the collection consists of collected pamphlets, periodicals, and newspapers on trade union activities in Africa, spanning from the 1950s to the 1970s.
Many files in the collection provide insight into the formation and development of the trade union movements in African countries such as Kenya, Uganda, Liberia, and Tanganyika (now Tanzania); criticism by African affiliates of the ICFTU administration; and the split between the All-African Trade Union Federation and the ICFTU. The papers also document conspiracy and bribery charges within the Kenya Federation of Labour, some of which implicate the CIA.
Arrangement
Series I-III are arranged in rough chronological order. In Series IV-VI, printed materials are grouped by country of origin. Series VII is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
The collection is organized into seven series:
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence, Biography, and Speeches, 1939-1971
Series II: CIO, AFL-CIO, and Other Organizing Files, 1937-1974
Series III: ICFTU Files, 1958-1971
Series IV: African Pamphlets and Periodicals, 1956-1972
Series V: News Clippings, 1956-1965
Series VI: African Newspapers, 1955-1964
Series VII: Photographs, circa 1930-1969
Pamphlets.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Communism -- United States.; Africa.; Communism -- History.; Africa |x Politics and government |y 1960-; Clippings (information artifacts); Ethiopia.; Casablanca (Morocco); African Americans |x Employment.; African American labor union members.; Correspondence.; Uganda.; Minutes (administrative records); Press releases.; Liberia.; Kenya.; Tanganyika.; Sudan.; Periodicals; Speeches.; Reports.; African Americans -- Civil rights.; Civil rights workers.; Working class |z Africa.; Kenya |x Politics and government |v Addresses, essays, lectures.; Addis Ababa (Ethiopia); Photographs.; African Americans |x Suffrage.; United States. Central Intelligence Agency; Meany, George, 1894-1980; Haywood, Allan S., 1888-1953; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Area Committee for East, Central, and Southern Africa; All-African Trade Union Federation; African Labour College; AFL-CIO; Bryher, 1894-1983; Corey, Lewis; Negro American Labor Council; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People; Kenya Federation of Labour; Confederation of East African Trade Unions; Welsh, Miriam; Pan-African Trade Congress; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Welsh, Edward K., 1902-1979; Lovestone, Jay.; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; McKay, Claude, 1890-1948; Mboya, Tom; Lubembe, Clement K., 1929-; International Communist Opposition; International Confederation of Free Trade Unions; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952
- Series I: Correspondence, Biography and Speeches, 1939-1971
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Correspondence, Biography, and Speeches, 1939-1971 includes Welsh's personal and political correspondence (mostly incoming), notes, a poem, and speeches made prior to his departure for Africa. Also included is a short biographical sketch. Among Welsh's correspondents are W.E.B. Du Bois; Claude McKay; Langston Hughes; the writer Bryher; politician and diplomat W. Averell Harriman; A. Philip Randolph; Lewis Corey; Allan S. Haywood; Jay Lovestone, director of the Department of International Affairs, AFL-CIO; Clement K. Lubembe, deputy general secretary of the Kenya Federation of Labour; and Tom Mboya, general secretary of the Kenya Federation of Labour and Chairman of the ICFTU Area Committee for East, Central, and Southern Africa.
  - Biographical, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Addresses and Speeches, 1940-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: CIO, AFL-CIO, and Other Organizing Files, 1937-1974
  Series II: CIO, AFL-CIO, and Other Organizing Files, 1937-1974 consists of correspondence, minutes, telegrams, resolutions, lists, leaflets, programs, invitations, employment permits, leases, and addresses and speeches that provide insight into Welsh's early career as a labor organizer. Some materials document Welsh's work for the CIO from 1937 to 1955 as a field representative organizing workers in the North and South, as well as in the Panama Canal Zone. Other files concern his membership in the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) and his later union activities during the 1950s and 1960s. These activities included organizing drives to unionize black workers, an effort which contributed to the formation of the Negro American Labor Council.
  - CIO, 1937-1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AFL-CIO, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AFL-CIO, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Canal Zone, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Personal Finances (medical, leases, in Africa), 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Taxi Drivers Strike, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - NAACP Convention Materials, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Urban League of Greater New York, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Negro American Labor Council, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Black Trade Unionists Committee, NYC Central Labor Council, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series III: International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (ICFTU) Files, 1958-1971
  Series III: International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (ICFTU) Files, 1958-1971 includes correspondence, telegrams, reports, agendas, circulars, speeches, photographs, documentation of financial transactions, and news releases. Of particular interest is material on Welsh's appointment as ICFTU representative in Africa and reports on union activities in Liberia, Kenya, Uganda, and Tanganyika (now Tanzania). Also included is a list of ICFTU field representatives in Africa, Asia, and Latin America; a draft of the Constitution of the Confederation of East African Trade Unions; a report on the First All-African Trade Union Conference; and records of the Pan-African Trade Congress held in Casablanca in 1961. Additional documents deal with CIA involvement in Kenya; the formation of the African Labour College in Uganda, which provided educational training for trade unionists in Africa; and the opposition to Tom Mboya's affiliation with the ICFTU by African countries that wanted to operate independently. The series also includes speeches made by heads of African states at a summit conference held in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia in 1963; a description of union activity and efforts to create a national trade union center in the Sudan; and financial accounts and a proposed program of organization and education within the Kenya Federation of Labour.
  - ICFTU: Appointments in Africa, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - ICFTU: Statement to UN, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - ICFTU: Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - ICFTU: Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - ICFTU: Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - ICFTU: Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - ICFTU: Official Correspondence and Bulletins, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - ICFTU: Africa - Speeches, Reports, Resolutions, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - ICFTU: Africa - Speeches, Reports, Resolutions, 1963-1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - ICFTU: East, Central, and Southern Africa Area Committee, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - ICFTU: African Labour College, Uganda, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - ICFTU: Africa - Finances, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - ICFTU: Kenya, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sudan, 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - All African Trade Union Conference (Casablanca), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tanganyika Federation of Labour, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Uganda, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Ethiopia, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Summit Conference of Independent African States (Addis Ababa), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Program - Honoring the President of Liberia, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series IV: African Pamphlets and Periodicals, 1956-1972
  A substantial portion of the periodicals in Series IV: African Pamphlets and Periodicals, 1956-1972 concern trade union activities in East and West African countries. Most of the pamphlets relate to nonunion activities, but there are a few pamphlets published by the ICFTU, the International Labor Organization (ILO), and the United Nations. There are three folders of miscellaneous pamphlets and periodicals with no direct bearing on trade unions in Africa. These publications will serve researchers interested in the trade union movement from an African perspective.
  - Gold Coast Today, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Kenya, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Nigeria, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Uganda, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Spearhead: The Pan-African Review, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ethiopia, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Voice of Africa, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Reporter, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Reporter, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ethiopia Mirror, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Pan Africa, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - West Africa, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Pamphlets and Periodicals, 1956-1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Pamphlets and Periodicals, 1963-1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series V: News Clippings, 1957-1963
  The files in Series V: Clippings, 1956-1965 are a rich source of materials for research into African trade union activities. Most clippings include dates, but only a few include the names of the newspapers. One file is from the U.S. press.
  - Uganda, 1957-1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Kenya, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Tanganyika, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ghana, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ethiopia, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - United States, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Northern Rhodesia, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - South Africa, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - African Students in Bulgaria, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - MOSHI - Afro-Asian Conference, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1956-1965 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series VI: African Newspapers, 1955-1964
  The miscellaneous selection of issues in Series VI: African Newspapers 1955-1964 contains material relevant to trade union history in various African countries.
  - Uganda Argus, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Uganda Argus, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Uganda Nation, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Uganda Nation, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Ethiopian Herald, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Voice of Ethiopia, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - East African Standard(Kenya), 1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - East African Standard(Kenya), 1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Daily Nation(Kenya), 1962-1964 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - MFANYI KAZI(Kenya), 1963 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Daily Listener(Liberia), 1964 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Liberian Age, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Liberian Star, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Egyptian Gazette, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Ghanaian Times, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Cameroon Times, Jul 23, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Daily/Sunday Times, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Nigerian Daily Sketch, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Daily Express(Nigeria), 1964 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - West African Pilot(Nigeria), 1964 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Nigerian Morning Post, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Nigerian Tribune, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - West African Worker(ICFTU Publication), 1955, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Assorted African Newspapers, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Series VII: Photographs, circa 1930-1969
  Series VII: Photographs is comprised of black-and-white photographs that document Welsh's work for the CIO, AFL-CIO, and other labor organizations in Panama, Africa, and the United States, especially during the 1950s and 1960s. The series contains group shots and portraits of Welsh, mostly from his years in Africa. The images from Panama include shots of various meetings, banquets, and speeches (including several from the March of Dimes), as well as photographs of seamen at the Panama Canal. There are also images from the Summit of Independent African States in Addis Abbaba, Ethiopia in May 1963 and three images from a folder labeled "Pictures - Africa," which consist of a group portrait featuring Welsh, an image of Welsh and another man holding up an embroidered shirt, and a candid photograph of Welsh and other men at the 14th Constitutional Convention of the CIO in 1952. Other images in the series are mostly photographs taken by news services of contemporary events in African nations during the 1950s and 1960s, as well as a few postcards and some group shots and portraits of various individuals.
  - General, circa 1950-1969 (Box Tamiment Shared A003, Folder 1)
  - Panama, circa 1949-1953 (Box Tamiment Shared A003, Folder 2)
  - "Pictures - Africa", circa 1950-1969 (Box Tamiment Shared A003, Folder 3)
  - Summit of Independent African States, May 1963 (Box Tamiment Shared A003, Folder 4)
  - Welsh, Edward Portraits and Group Shots, circa 1930-1969 (Box Tamiment Shared A003, Folder 5)